BIOGRAPHICAL SKETCH

(Last updated: 20/04/2020)

Miguel Tábuas Pereira, MD, PhD Candidate

Consultant Neurologist and Clinical Researcher Centro Hospitalar e Universitário de Coimbra Praceta Prof. Mota Pinto, 3000-075, Coimbra, Portugal

Date of Birth: 19/09/1987 Head of the Memory Clinic miguelatcp@gmail.com +351 913 166 131







A. EDUCATION/TRAINING:



INSTITUTION AND LOCATION	DEGREE	YEAR(s)	FIELD OF STUDY
University of Coimbra	MD	2005-2011	Medicine
University College of	PgDip	2017-	Clinical
London		ongoing	Neurology
University of Coimbra	PhD	2018-	Neuroscience
		ongoing	

B. POSITIONS AND HONORS

Positions and Employment

2018 Neurologist, Coimbra University Hospital

2013 Neurology Residency, Coimbra University Hospital

Other Experience and Professional Memberships

2016 to date – Member of the Higher Cortical Functions Scientific Panel of the European Academy of Neurology (EAN)

2016 to date - Member of the Education Committee of the EAN

Honors

2017 Winner of the 1st Neurology Tournament (Portuguese Society of Neurology)

2005 Gold Medal in the Ibero-America Physic Olympiads

2004 Bronze Medal in the San Paolo Mathematics Olympiads

C. SELECTED PEER-REVIEWED PUBLICATIONS IN JOURNAL WITH IMPACT FACTOR)

Faster Cortical Thinning and Surface Area Loss in Presymptomatic and Symptomatic C9orf72 Repeat Expansion Adult Carriers. Le Blanc G, Pomerleau VJ, McCarthy J, et al. (including <u>Tábuas-Pereira M</u>). Ann Neurol. 2020.

- 2. **Neuronal Pentraxin 2: A Synapse-Derived CSF Biomarker in Genetic Frontotemporal Dementia.** Van der Ende EL; Xiao M, Xu D, et al. (including <u>Tábuas-Pereira M</u>). J Neurol Neurosurg Psychiatry. 2020.
- 3. Alzheimer's Disease Genetics: Review of Novel Loci Associated with Disease. <u>Tábuas-Pereira M</u>, Santana I, Guerreiro R, Bras J. Curr Genet Med Rep 2020.
- 4. **Two sisters with myoclonus and ataxia**. <u>Pereira M</u>, Durães J, Carmo, MC. Pract Neurol. 2020.
- 5. Plasma glial fibrillary acidic protein is raised in progranulin-associated frontotemporal dementia. Heller C, Foiani MS, Moore K, Convery R, et al. (including <u>Tábuas-Pereira M</u>). J Neurol Neurosurg Psychiatry. 2020.
- 6. Headache intensity is associated with increased white matter lesion burden in CADASIL patients. <u>Tábuas-Pereira M</u>, Varela R, Beato-Coelho J, et al. J Clin Neurosci. 2020.
- 7. **Single Word Repetition Predicts Long-Term Outcome of Aphasia Caused by an Ischemic Stroke**. <u>Tábuas-Pereira M</u>, Beato-Coelho J, Ribeiro J, Nogueira AR, Cruz L, Silva F, Sargento-Freitas J, Cordeiro G, Santana I. J Stroke Cerebrovasc Dis. 2020.
- 8. A worldwide cohort study of age at symptom onset and death and disease duration in genetic frontotemporal dementia. Moore KM, Nicholas J, Grossman M, et al. (including <u>Tábuas-Pereira M</u>). Lancet Neurology. 2020.
- 9. Lower CSF Amyloid-Beta₁₋₄₂ Predicts a Higher Mortality Rate in Frontotemporal Dementia. Vieira D, Durães J, Baldeiras I, et al. (including <u>Tábuas-Pereira M</u>). Diagnostics (Basel). 2019.
- 10. Serum Neurofilament Light Chain in Genetic Frontotemporal Dementia: A Longitudinal, Multicentre Cohort Study. Van der Ende EL, Meeter LH, Poos JM, et al. (including Tábuas-Pereira M). Lancet Neurol. 2019.
- 11. Increased CSF tau is associated with a higher risk of seizures in patients with Alzheimer's disease. <u>Tábuas-Pereira M</u>, Durães J, Lopes J, et al. Epilepsy Behav. 2019.
- 12. **Education modulates brain maintenance in presymptomatic frontotemporal dementia.** Gazzina S, Grassi M, Premi E, et al. (including <u>Tábuas-Pereira M</u>). J Neurol Neurosurg Psychiatry. 2019.
- 13. Functional network resilience to pathology in presymptomatic genetic frontotemporal dementia. Rittman T, Borchert R, Jones S, et al. (including Tábuas-Pereira M). Neurobiol Aging. 2019
- 14. The inner fluctuations of the brain in presymptomatic Frontotemporal **Dementia: The chronnectome fingerprint.** Premi E, Calhoun VD, Diano M, et al. (including <u>Tábuas-Pereira M</u>). Neuroimage. 2019
- 15. Increased risk of melanoma in C9ORF72 repeat expansion carriers: A case-control study. <u>Tábuas-Pereira M</u>, Almendra L, Almeida MR, Durães J, Pinho A, Matos A, Negrão L, Geraldo A, Santana I. Muscle Nerve. 2019
- 16. Discriminative capacity and construct validity of the Clock Drawing Test in Mild Cognitive Impairment and Alzheimer's disease. Duro D, Freitas S, Tábuas-Pereira M, Santiago B, Botelho MA, Santana I. Clin Neuropsychol. 2018
- 17. The Head Turning Sign in Dementia and Mild Cognitive Impairment: Its Relationship to Cognition, Behavior, and Cerebrospinal Fluid Biomarkers.

- Durães J*, <u>Tábuas-Pereira M*</u>, Araújo R, Duro D, Baldeiras I, Santiago B, Santana I. *Dement Geriatr Cogn Disord*. 2018 Aug 9;46(1-2):42-49. doi: 10.1159/000486531.
- 18. Aphasia Rapid Test: Translation, Adaptation and Validation Studies for the Portuguese Population. <u>Tábuas-Pereira M</u>, Freitas S, Beato-Coelho J, et al. Acta Med Port. 2018 May 30;31 (5):265-271. doi: 10.20344/amp.9090
- 19. Validity and Clinical Utility of Different Clock Drawing Test Scoring Systems in Multiple Forms of Dementia. Duro D, <u>Tábuas-Pereira M</u>, Freitas S, Santiago B, Botelho MA, Santana I. J Geriatr Psychiatry Neurol. 2018 Jan 1:891988718774432. doi: 10.1177/0891988718774432.
- 20. Underlying Biological Processes in Mild Cognitive Impairment: Amyloidosis Versus Neurodegeneration. Santana I, Baldeiras I, Santiago B, Duro D, Freitas S, Pereira MT, Almeida MR, Oliveira CR. J Alzheimers Dis. 2018 Mar 16. doi: 10.3233/JAD-179908.
- 21. Addition of the Aβ42/40 ratio to the cerebrospinal fluid biomarker profile increases the predictive value for underlying Alzheimer's disease dementia in mild cognitive impairment. Baldeiras I, Santana I, Leitão MJ, Gens H, Pascoal R, Tábuas-Pereira M, Beato-Coelho J, Duro D, Almeida MR, Oliveira CR. Alzheimers Res Ther. 2018 Mar 20;10(1):33. doi: 10.1186/s13195-018-0362-2.
- 22. Alzheimer's Disease Assessment Scale Cognitive Subscale (ADAS-Cog): Normative Data for the Portuguese Population. Nogueira J, Freitas S, Duro D, Tábuas-Pereira M, Guerreiro M, Almeida J, Santana I. Acta Med Port. 2018 Feb 28;31(2):94-100. doi: 10.20344/amp.8859. Epub 2018 Feb 28.
- 23. <u>Intracranial Internal Carotid Artery Wall Calcification in Ischemic Strokes Treated with Thrombolysis</u>. <u>Tábuas-Pereira M</u>, Sargento-Freitas J, Silva F, Parra J, Mendes P, Seara V, Mesquita M, Baptista M, Cordeiro G, Cunha L. *Eur Neurol*. 2018;79(1-2):21-26. doi: 10.1159/000477901. Epub 2017 Nov 13.
- 24. Clinical Reasoning: A 55-year-old man with rapidly progressive dementia and parkinsonism
- <u>Tábuas-Pereira M</u>, Santana I, Santo GC. *Neurology*. 2017 Oct 10;89(15):e182-e187. doi: 10.1212/WNL.000000000004495. Epub 2017 Oct 9.
- 25. <u>Neurosonology Accuracy for Isolated Acute Vestibular Syndromes</u>. <u>Tábuas-Pereira M</u>, Sargento-Freitas J, Isidoro L, Silva F, Galego O, Nunes C, Cordeiro G, Cunha L. *J Ultrasound Med*. 2017 Dec;36(12):2545-2550. doi: 10.1002/jum.14301. Epub 2017 Jul 10.
- 26. <u>European Academy of Neurology Resident and Research Fellow Section: innovations and future direction in 2017</u>. Papp V, Klingelhoefer L, Zis P, Melis M, <u>Tábuas-Pereira M</u>, Macerollo A, Sauerbier A. *Eur J Neurol*. 2017 Sep;24(9):e51-e53. doi: 10.1111/ene.13352. Epub 2017 Jun 21.
- 27. Association between butyrylcholinesterase and cerebrospinal fluid biomarkers in Alzheimer's disease patients. Gabriel AJ, Almeida MR, Ribeiro MH, Durães J, <u>Tábuas-Pereira M</u>, Pinheiro AC, Pascoal R, Santana I, Baldeiras I. Neurosci Lett. 2017 Feb 22;641:101-106. doi: 10.1016/j.neulet.2017.01.036. Epub 2017 Jan 17.
- 28. **Tremor Frequency Assessment by iPhone® Applications: Correlation with EMG Analysis**. Araújo R, <u>Tábuas-Pereira</u> M, Almendra L, Ribeiro J, Arenga M, Negrão L, Matos A, Morgadinho A, Januário C. J Parkinsons Dis. 2016 Oct 19;6(4):717-72.

- 29. **Prosopagnosia as the Presenting Symptom of Whipple Disease.** <u>Tábuas-Pereira M</u>, Vicente M, Coelho F, Santana I. Cogn Behav Neurol. 2016 Jun;29(2):100-6. doi: 10.1097/WNN.0000000000000001.
- 30. <u>Prognosis of Early-Onset vs. Late-Onset Mild Cognitive Impairment: Comparison of Conversion Rates and Its Predictors.</u> <u>Tábuas-Pereira M</u>, Baldeiras I, Duro D, Santiago B, Ribeiro MH, Leitão MJ, Oliveira C, Santana I. Geriatrics (Basel). 2016
- 31. [Mini-Mental State Examination: Screening and Diagnosis of Cognitive Decline, Using New Normative Data]. Santana I, Duro D, Lemos R, Costa V, Pereira M, Simões MR, Freitas S. Acta Med Port. 2016.
- 32. **Biparietal variant of Alzheimer's disease: a rare presentation of a common disease.** Marques IB, <u>Tábuas-Pereira M</u>, Milheiro M, Santana I. BMJ Case Rep. 2015 Jan 5;2015. pii: bcr2014207011. doi: 10.1136/bcr-2014-207011.

D. RESEARCH SUPPORT (LAST 5 YEARS):

Tecnifar Grant "The relationship between white matter lesions with pain sensitivity dysregulation in patients with migraine". (2015) (PI: Miguel Tábuas-Pereira)

E. BIBLIOMETRIC INDICATORS

Miguel Tábuas-Pereira | Miguel Pereira | Tábuas-Pereira, M. [ORCID ID | https://orcid.org/0000-0002-3988-614X | SCOPUS ID: 56493155900]

- 1. Total number of citations (google scholar): 95
- 2. h factor (google scholar): 5
- 3. Cumulative impact factor: 156.477
- 4. Number of papers with impact factor over 7 during the last 5 years: 7
- 5. Number and impact of papers as corresponding or last author during

the last 5 years: 12, 27.809